this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software are you ready to take the next
step in your career as an engineer Penn
State a leader in engineering education
offers an online program that lets you
earn your masters and software
engineering without leaving your current
position you can complete your degree in
as little as two years and GREs are not
required for admission learn more by
visiting us at world campus PSU edu
slash se radio hello this is Jeremy Joan
for software engineering radio today I'm
speaking with Tyler McMullen Tyler is
the CTO of fast Lee where he is
responsible for system architecture and
least the company's technology vision
previously he worked on text analysis
and recommendations at script I'll be
speaking with Tyler about what a CDN is
why and how a project would use one and
what goes into its creation Tyler
welcome to software engineering radio
thank you happy to be here let's start
things off by defining a content
delivery network
sure yeah content delivery network at
its core is really a geographically
distributed network of servers that's
serve the content for a website or an
application what kind of information can
be stored in a content delivery network
well I mean really it could be just
about anything I mean for most CDNs out
there like it's really anything that can
be delivered over HTTP that could be
videos and images CSS all the way to
like actual web pages and api's and yeah
all sorts of things you can store pretty
much anything how how would you
differentiate the role of a CDN from
object storage like for example s3 sure
No
so something like s3 is much more
focused on making sure that an object
will always be there right like if you
lose an object in s3 that's a--that's a
huge problem for them whereas fastly
like you know one of our big benefits is
that you know which comes to shove we
can actually lose objects right it's a
cache rather than an actual like storage
system I database right what we focus
much more on is making sure that the
delivery of the objects are actually
really fast
the main differentiator is the fact that
you don't have to worry about losing it
because you know that the data will
always be there to retrieve again if you
were to lose it exactly like the way
that the way that our CDN works and this
this has changed over the course of
years I'm sure we'll get to that later
but we function as a proxy right so
we're not supposed to be the actual like
primary storage for for really anything
right so we function as the server that
sits in between you and your customers
and you were saying that since it's this
is more of a cache type of situation how
would you distinguish what fastly does
recede ian's do compared to something
like memcache or Redis yeah so I mean
it's it's similar in a lot of ways right
like its core they're both like they're
to try to you know make the delivery of
these the application the delivery of
the content itself faster something like
memcache to Redis though is much more
focused on like being available during
the generation of the content itself
right they're also not right through or
read through caches so fastly and cbons
in general at this point really function
as like a read through
proxy cash right so a user might you
know request some particular piece of
content from your site we get that
request if we don't have it well then go
look it up and then the next version
that comes along we won't have to go
look it up because we'll already have it
next I'd like to ask are there are any
common misconceptions about what a CDN
can or can't do well there's a variety
these you know I hear these all the time
actually you know probably the biggest
one I would say is there's there's
always this conception that a CDN is
actually like supposed to be pushed to
kind of like what you were what you
would expect from something like s3 that
is the primary storage for a thing and
to be clear there have been CBN's that
function like that in the past that's
that's really like an uncommon model now
though so one of the interesting effects
of that is that if everything is if it's
supposed to be a proxy if you know all
your users can read through it that
actually puts us in an interesting place
right so we can actually serve things
that aren't
cashable right so dynamic content as
well can be served just the same
thorough CDN as long as SC VM provides
you the ability to distinguish between
cashable and non catchable things you
were saying that in the past there was
this perception that scenes were
supposed to be pushed - why was that not
a good idea or why have things changed
now so I think a lot of it comes down to
how the internet how websites and
applications are built these days you
know in the past the internet was and
websites were a lot more static than
they are now you know you would have
your HTML your regular HTML you pushed
your images you would push your well I'm
not even CSS back then really but but
all sorts of things like that and you
know that site was fairly static until
you decided to change it now we have a
lot more in the way of like
user-generated content and dynamic
content in general right so it makes a
lot more sense to allow the CDN to fetch
new objects and new things that didn't
exist before right without you having to
actually like you know go go actually
push them up to the CDN mmm just because
nowadays things are more frequently
changing on the web sites right if you
can imagine like a large social network
you know if every time a post was made
they had to actually push that post to a
like local network of servers that would
be like extremely not scalable
right okay another thing I'd like to
define before we go further is the idea
of an origin and an edge within the
context of seed Ian's could you describe
that yeah yeah so an origin in our case
could be anything from like a single
server that you're hosting on you know
some Linode or something like that all
the way to like a you know multiple data
centers that you as as one of our
customers you know have hosting in like
AWS all around the world for instance so
the origin is really just you know the
source of the content you know we look
at the origin as being like the source
of truth right and the edge for us
anyway is is our data center spread
around the world right
you know the edge is kind of an
interesting topic at the moment just
because there are so many different
definitions that people use for it but
from our perspective anyway the the
edges you know our 50-plus data center
spread around the world basically the
users application would be the origin
and the edge is the CDN which is
retrieving all of the canonical data
from the origin sure and I mean even
that is changing though now it's like a
lot of what is going on with with new
development and CBN's and you know at
the edge in general there are certain
cases where we're actually starting to
use the edge as the origin itself as
well but I'm sure we can get into that
later yeah for sure we have to remember
to to come back to that so another
aspect of CD ends is when users
requested there they're hitting a host
name so one of the things that I want to
talk about is DNS so so first off could
you give like a high-level overview of
what DNS does sure so probably the most
common metaphor that's used for for DNS
is the idea of a phone book you know so
if you wanted to look someone up in the
phone book
or if you wanted to call someone
effectively you would you would look
them up in the phone book you would go
alright well let me see I will look them
up by name and I'll get a number for
them well it's not so different than the
way DNS works except in this case that
that phonebook is in fact hosted by your
ISP typically and so when you want to
find a site let's say you you're trying
to go to Stassi comm you would
your your computer would actually send a
small packet that would go out to the
DNS server that your ISP is hosting that
ISP the ISPs DNS server if it knows
about it would have just immediately
respond with all right here are the IP
address or the IP addresses that I know
of for that site and if it doesn't it
actually is itself yet another reverse
proxy and we'll go look it up for you
and then remember it for the next time
and as a developer how do you configure
website to serve content from a specific
domain
okay so since this is a actually like
more complicated than it might seem
but like the typical way this is done is
that you know if you have a a sub-domain
let's say it's www or site com you would
actually set a DNS cname on that you
provide you tell your DNS provider that
you want to put a cname record for that
particular sub domain and that cname
would then essentially I mean
effectively it's it's similar to an HTTP
redirect you say ok this website is
actually going to be pointing to this
other website right and then your DNS
resolver your ISPs DNS resolver would
then do that that recursive look up to
see ok you know here what is the IP
address for the the redirected domain so
in our case that would be you know your
going to Prague not fastly Nets for your
site and so you know your DNS would go
look up pronto fastly net which would
then provide an IP address and like this
is actually a big portion of how CBMs
are able to do geographic distribution
well is the fact that when your DNS
provider goes and looks up okay what is
prod that fastly about net it will get a
different response depending on where
you are in the world what's making the
decision on which server to pass you to
when you make that request like where
does that part live right so as part of
the DNS lookup it ends up eventually if
you're if you're you have it a cname
pointed to prophecy net for instance
that ends up eventually hitting one of
our servers so we have our own DNS
servers that will sit there and go okay
well you know if if this DNS request is
coming from such-and-such location well
I know that the closest place that I can
send that user is actually over here
right so if you're a you know in LA for
instance you would get a you know you
would end up getting an IP address that
is one of our data centers in LA
hmm okay so it's actually a DNS server
that's managed by fastly oh yeah
absolutely okay next I'd like to discuss
why someone would use a CDN so for one
of the reasons would be the performance
so first off how can a CDN improve
performance for someone's application
so okay so like at the most basic form
you know the way the cbn works is that
you know improves it improves
performance by making sure that when a
user requests a particular piece of
content that piece of content is close
to the user already so this is
especially important like it's important
even even inside the US and inside like
other like highly developed countries
but if you're or not even highly
developed countries but countries that
are close to the origin but you know it
applies even more if you're in some
place like Australia right if your
Origin server is say in Ashburn Virginia
and your user is coming from Australia
well okay if you if you want to get a
piece of content that is especially a
large piece of content right that's
gonna involve quite a few round trips
back and forth and you know the speed of
light is fast but it's not infinitely
fast right so it's it can end up being
quite a bit faster to be able to just
get that piece of content from somewhere
that is right next door to you
and so so there's a bunch of different
ways of that that actually makes things
faster right so part of it is just
network latency right but then if you
consider the fact that you know
especially in like the Internet as it
exists today like the the time it takes
to generate that content might be
non-trivial right and so that's where
the cache itself comes in right so if
you're able to then just serve a piece
of content that is already static at
this point it's the RT is just sitting
there on on one of our servers that's
you know in addition to the network
optimization portion it's also quite a
bit faster just because you don't have
to generate the content and then
furthermore if you have a piece of
dynamic content right where in the case
that let's say it's like something
that's personalized for that particular
user where you can actually cache it or
it contains private information or
something like that
if you pass that through through fastly
at least and this isn't the case for all
CD ends but one of the things that we do
is we keep a connection open to your
origin and so this ends up coming back
to like you know fairly basic like TCP
optimization type of stuff so TCP has
this concept of slow start so if you
send an initial request you you open
your connection with TCP you can only
send a few packets initially before you
then have to wait for an acknowledgment
right and so over time that window that
TCP
congestion window will increase up to a
certain amount that certain amounts
should be roughly near like what your
total bandwidth is that's available
between you and the origin server so
what we do affects is you know if you
are going for a piece of dynamic content
you'll go to the fastly server that is
nearby you and then we will have a
connection that is already open back to
your origin server so you're not having
to wait for that TCP congestion window
for nearly as much time so even just
network optimizations themselves can
make a pretty huge difference in terms
of like a rough metric or percentage how
much faster have you seen CD ins make a
application well again this is something
that really is a super application
dependent bouncer right but we've seen
things where you know sites go from like
20 second 15 second load times down to 2
or 3 seconds oh ok so it can be it can
be massive right and so much this is
also like geographically dependent as
well hmm
and in terms of whether it's the latency
being improved or the data being served
statically or the tcp slow-start which
part makes the most difference is going
to be dependent on the application -
right oh yeah absolutely so if you'd
like a particularly slow origin server
like you know one of our major customers
in the early days it was a large wiki
and you know it takes a long time like
those PHP based wiki servers well they
have a lot of work to do - like to be
able to generate all the content on a
particular page and so like that was a
great example of like all right we can
just serve this static content that is
static until it changes of course
directly from the edge without having to
do all of that all of that generation
how can using a CDN improve reliability
and can you also explain how the CDN
itself is redundant it's a really
interesting question actually like the
the way the CDN increases reliability is
the fact that like the CDN itself is
like the way I like to think about is
the CDN is actually fairly simple right
like when you when you're just
delivering content when you're just
delivering static content there's
there's no database lookups there's no
you know we have fairly few things that
can actually go down on one of our
servers right but really what it comes
down to is the fact that
that helps a little bit right like the
the fact that we're just delivering
static content in most cases but what
helps the most is just the fact that we
have thousands of servers run around the
world and so we actually have multiple
layers built into the network to prevent
outage of a single server or even a
single data center from even being
noticeable by by your users so part of
that is DNS right so you know as I was
saying the the DNS requests that that
ends up coming through from your
end-users ends up hitting one of our DNS
servers right that DNS is actually
served via something called anycast so
what this effectively is is that you
know we have a single IP address which
is actually served from multiple
different locations right so we have
many locations around the world saying
like hey I have you know BM BGP I have
this IP address you can get this from me
so if a data center goes down that DNS
request will actually just be rounded by
BGP to someone else furthermore if a
datacenter went down we also know that
internally inside our network so we can
just say with our DNS server like ah
this one's down let's send them to the
next closest server but beyond that we
also have redundancy built into the data
centers themselves so if a single server
goes down that's actually noticed by our
switch itself right and so we have a
monitoring system that runs on the
switch with in collaboration with a
piece of software that's running on the
server and so when a server stops
responding when a health check fails for
the server we actually just remove it
from the switch entirely and so any
content that would have been requests
from that server will then be routed to
a different server within the same
datacenter
moreover we also store the content
multiple times within a data center so
the failure of a single server you know
not only will the requests still be
served but it'll still be served with
roughly the same speed as well so you've
got the data stored in multiple places
for redundancy
you've got servers kind of all over the
world in terms of spreading the
redundancy that way and then at the data
center level you also have monitoring to
make sure that none of the data centers
are affected by servers going down yeah
exactly like that the type of monitoring
needs to be you know some second kind of
like response time
when a server goes down we know just we
know immediately the thing is when
you're serving like five million plus
requests per second like even one second
of downtime is a lot of requests right I
want to go back briefly to you were
describing anycast just so that I make
sure I understand correctly you were
saying you could have a single IP and
Wednesday my ISP starts to perform a DNS
lookup to that IP then it could actually
go to any one of your servers that are
you know located throughout the world
yeah yeah at its core and I'm sure our
network engineering team is just going
to hate me because I'm sure I'm going to
butcher the description of anycast here
but I mean effectively what you're doing
is you're advertising the BGP the border
gateway protocol that any of these
particular any of these data centers can
serve this particular IP address and
what what ends up happening there is
that on the intermediary routers between
that the router will be able to figure
out all right well I have multiple
routes I could take to get to this
particular IP address let me take the
one that has the least number of hops
and when we say hops we don't actually
mean hops in terms of IP addresses along
the way we actually mean hops in terms
of AAS numbers that is autonomous system
numbers so anycast
is a great is a great way to like
provide redundancy and provide like you
know failover capabilities but it's also
like fairly it's a it's a blunt
instrument right so it's fairly hard to
to direct traffic accurately using
anycast at a high level when you say
autonomous system what are you referring
to there so an autonomous system number
basically just describes an entire
network right so when you say that like
when you do say hey who is on a
particular IP address and look up who
owns that that's actually looking up
what the a s number is of that IP
address and then whose information is
connected with that a s number so fastly
has one a s number that we use for all
of them hmm okay next I'd like to talk
about how a CDN might be able to improve
security can you give some examples of
security related features that a CDN can
provide
sure so there's actually a bunch of
these I mean probably the most obvious
one is DDoS mitigation right and part of
this actually just comes down to like
the basic architecture of a CDN like the
fact that we are sitting in between your
end users and you and your origin server
means that any attacks that like let's
say you know syn floods that would
normally be hitting your origin server
would be hitting us instead right so we
sent there kind of as a shield to all
those sorts of attacks but it actually
goes beyond that right so when you have
you know some CDN specifically fastly
has the concept of a Web Application
Firewall right so what that ends up
meaning is that requests that are
flowing through the system we can also
then check against all sorts of filters
to look for common the sorts of attacks
you know be that a sequel injection
attack or really anything hmm and so you
can check for those and block them
before the origin system even ever sees
them yeah exactly
and that's you know that's even more
true for the DDoS mitigation right so
like in the case of a syn flood you
wouldn't even see any of those you
wouldn't see a single packet right
because in the case of a syn flood
effectively what the attacker is trying
to do is open a ton of connections
however those connections aren't real
you know they're fake connections and
the whole idea behind a syn flood is
that when you open a connection when you
send that syn packet initially to a
server that actually takes up some
states in the server's operating system
that state is essentially saying ok you
know I have this person on the other end
that is looking to open a connection you
know I'm gonna be like you know I'm
gonna do the handshake with them now so
it has to remember that and so when you
then suddenly send hundreds of thousands
millions or more sins this can actually
cause like quite a bit of quite a bit of
strain on any particular server right so
fastly has mitigations in place for that
so you know we can handle those sorts of
attacks and you would never see a single
bottom hmm
are there any ways that introducing a
CDN can actually increase your attack
surface
well I mean yeah certainly it's anytime
you would like I feel like any software
engineer realizes that you know anytime
you introduce any dependency into your
system like it you know it changes your
attack surface the very least like the
ultimate goal here is that like when you
use a CDN or use really any third-party
system that that effectively you're
you're reducing your attack surface
ultimately but you're introducing a new
attack surface right so yeah I mean if
you look at like certain incidents that
have happened in the past it's certainly
possible that that things can happen but
you know we do all all sorts of things
to prevent that we have an entire
security team that is constantly
attacking our system by themselves to
find any sorts of holes that would that
would normally be that would be found by
attackers most high-profile security
incident I can think of with CD ends is
the cloud bleed book where there was a
memory leak issue and things like
cookies and API tokens were being leaked
by Ed servers so I just wanted to get
your thoughts on that sure sure
I mean that kind of thing can happen to
anybody but you know it's just a matter
of you know what your response is to it
when it does happen and you know just
doing everything you can to prevent it
ahead of time right so in the end it's
and anytime you use a managed service
you're you're placing some level of
trust in the system and so yeah I mean
yeah I mean if you think about it like
you know it's really a question of like
who you know how much do you trust like
your your how much do you trust any
third party provider like you know
someone like fastly is sitting between
you and your users like we put a lot of
effort into making sure that nothing bad
can happen there you know we don't
always succeed but we probably succeed a
lot more than you know
the vast majority the next thing I'd
like to go into is the different ways
that a CDN can be used so let's start
with static asset caching can you
describe how somebody that has a dynamic
site now would get started with using a
CDN for that
sure so there's many different ways that
you could approach this right like the
the way that I would typically suggest
is that you know you you're probably
serving your static assets and your
dynamic assets from the same domain it's
a small site in that case like the
easiest way to do this is really just to
change the entire site over to point to
the CDN and you know the the important
part with this like the really key part
is so okay so you set up your DNS but
like the most key thing is making sure
that the HTTP caching headers that
you're using are correct right so if it
were the case that like you were serving
dynamic content that was you know
personalized and the HTTP caching
headers said to cache it that could be
fairly dangerous right so I would say
that one of the first things you want to
do is make sure that your your your
caching headers are set up correctly the
alternative of course is that you know
you can set up a separate domain that is
used specifically for for serving static
content there are certain advantages to
that as well like specifically that
typically like if you have a dynamic
site you're using cookies using all
sorts of things that like actually bloat
the initial like requests and responses
by using a separate domain for that you
can actually shrink those down and
optimize them to the point where it's
just the bare minimum that's required
there so that's actually the primary
reason why people use separate domains
for that is really just to make sure
that like alright so if I'm using
enormous cookies on my dynamic side of
my site those don't have to be sent and
received every single time I send a
request for you know a single CSS file
for instance hmm okay so that's that
would be the main reason why you would
choose to have a different domain yeah
that's the biggest thing I mean the
other thing was you know there was
always the the the use case in the past
where people would set up many different
static domains so you would see like
static dot whatever one static that
whatever - and this was actually an
attempt to get around HTTP head of line
blocking but as it turns out if you're
using HTTP 2 or eventually quick this is
actually not even necessary because the
the head of line blocking problem
basically goes away
and you were describing that initially
you would recommend that someone changed
their entire site over to being backed
by the CDN but you were also talking
about dynamic content so in that case
how would someone set up their site to
be served entirely from the CD and even
though they have dynamic content sure I
mean the key thing to do there again
this kind this kind of comes back to the
HTTP caching headers so it's knowing you
know as you're generating that content
ok this piece of content is dynamic
versus this one being static the dynamic
one you would want to then set to be
private no cache and like there's all
sorts of great articles on the internet
about how to set that up correctly with
the cache control header but that's
really the key thing there though yeah
and so when we're talking about dynamic
content this could be things like API
calls as well so somebody makes a call
to say a JSON API and as long as the
HTTP headers always return no cache than
that that should be ok yeah that should
be just fine you know and this is this
is like kind of a great intro to like
one of the things that fastly does quite
a bit different than most other CDN so
what a lot of people consider to be
dynamic content I would argue is not
actually dynamic content so you're
talking about something like
user-generated content again kind of
going back to the wiki example that I
was getting before that content is not
actually dynamic it's it's static until
someone changes it I kind of in the same
sense as like everything else is static
until someone changes it and so one of
the key things that fastly provides is
this ability to remove content really
rapidly from around the world so we have
a purging system right so essentially
the idea with this is that you know you
can cache those you know supposedly
dynamic pages
until you know that they change right so
someone updates that page if someone
posts a new comment or or whatever this
gives you the ability to then and in
about 150 milliseconds remove that piece
of content from around the world which
will then let us cache a new version
when you talk about static content from
the perspective of the CDN
that's content that ya know it's content
that is I mean I like the key way that I
think about it is that it's content that
is reusable right even if that content
changes frequently if it's reusable
across different users across different
requests that content is effectively
cacheable what about content that is
restricted per user content that only
someone who's authenticated where the
page should be able to see sure so
there's a couple different ways to do
that like you know the most the most
common way if you're using a basic CDN
would be to treat that content as
dynamic and not cache it you can do some
more interesting things though for
instance we have quite a few customers
who actually do authentication in the
CPM which is kind of an interesting use
case I think so they can do that by
validating that the cookie that is on
that that request is is correct as valid
actually put that logic in the CDN
itself or we can even do like weirder
things and we can do this so fastly as a
concept of multiple requests that we
make to your origin for a single request
that a user makes to us so what we can
do is the user makes a request for
something that you know needs
authentication we then send a request
back to your origin saying hey is this
user is this user valid and how long are
they valid for and then we've remembered
that we cache that the CBM the exact
same way we cache anything else and then
we can go okay now we know that this
user is validated is authenticated so we
can just serve them the content that we
already have cached hmm so does that
mean that fastly is actually has some
kind of state to keep track of these
users so kind of yeah I mean you could
think of it that way I guess the way the
way I think of it is from the inside of
the CDN right like I you know how know
how the sausage is made and so I
effectively think of this as just you
know it's making multiple requests back
to the back to the origin and caching
them you know in the CDN and we would
cash anything so we're just caching the
authentication but effectively yeah it's
it's remembering state across requests
okay
and the this sort of authentication back
and forth that could be through cookies
or that could be through some other
method sure let me through cookies I
mean effectively I mean really what you
need is just an API on the other end
that knows whether or not a particular
cookie is is valid is all kind of
capable hmm
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
one hundred dollar infrastructure credit
at doco slash SE radio next i'd like to
talk about developing an application
with a CDN in mind the first question
would be does the introduction of a CDN
to a project impact development are
there things that the developer needs to
do differently in order to to add a CDN
so I think the biggest thing with this
is making sure that content that is
cacheable that you know is static or at
least temporarily static is separated as
much as possible from content that you
know to be private or dynamic so if you
had a single web page that had
everything built into it including the
dynamic and the static content well
that's gonna be hard to cache because we
can't really separate out what is static
and what is dynamic from that so if
instead what you can do is break that up
into multiple requests into multiple
responses such that we minimize the
number the size especially of the
dynamic content and instead break out
the static content into something that
can be cached that makes a big
difference there hmm in this case it
would be breaking out the dynamic
content into separate API calls is that
kind of what you had in mind that's kind
of what I have in mind yeah so you know
one one I mean a really simple example
of this is we have lots of media like
newspaper kind of websites that use
and a lot of times what you'll see when
you initially go to those sites is that
it's actually the same it's the same for
the vast majority of users and the only
difference is that at least at least
initially at least visibly is that your
name is in the top right corner right
and so if if you were generating that
entire page with just that little bit of
private like you know user specific
content there it's easy to make the
entire page and on cacheable even said
you can break that out into a separate
API call and fill it in later or even
use something like ESI I just side
includes in order to like input that
data then you can make much more of the
site cashable which proves the users
experience and also like reduces the
amount of load on your origin server but
quite a lot
you had mentioned ESI could you define
what that means sure ESI stands for edge
side includes and so what the SI is is a
it's a little markup language that can
be placed into HTML or XML or you know
even you can even like kind of abuse it
and put it inside of JSON but the whole
idea here is that it's something that
the CDN or even your like your server
can then parse and when it parses that
it finds oh this markup right here
should actually be replaced with the
content from this other page over here
alright so it lets you I mean you can
think of it as a template language
that's specifically made for the edge
it's actually been around for quite a
while but there are some certain issues
with it it's one of the problems with
this with ESI is that it's easy to it
it's effectively easy to DDoS yourself
with it but if you do it wrong so the
way that I would usually suggest to
people that they do this is actually
just by doing a client-side you know let
the let the JavaScript on your users
browser fill in the content that is
specifically private to them right okay
in the case of somebody having an
application where they haven't really
built for this Eden in mind but they
just want to get started quickly what
kind of options do they have
so probably easy so yeah I know there's
there's some pretty easy options they
have you know the easiest thing is okay
cool separate out your static content
make sure that your server is you know
setting those HTTP cache control headers
correctly and then just accept the fact
that like the the content on some of
those maybe it's the HTML for your pages
is going to be dynamic but the neat
thing is that you still as I was
mentioning earlier you still get quite a
bit of benefit from the CDN based on
those Network optimizations that we're
doing so even if your entire site was
dynamic and we actually have several
customers who don't cache anything there
instead like just using us for the
network optimization part you still get
quite a bit of benefit and in cases like
this are you talking about where someone
will go to a site and it'll be hitting
fastly first or is this the case of
where someone hits a site and they're
just using fastly to pull images or
other static things that are on the
dynamic page so I mean it's really both
right like so if you can specifically
set the HTTP headers correctly for the
static content will do the right thing
with that which is essentially to like
cache just the responses that are
actually cacheable right so really like
just i know i'm kind of like a broken
record here but like if you set to your
cache control headers correctly you can
put a CDN in front of it and it will it
should continue to function exactly the
way that you expect for someone to set
the cache control headers would that
normally have to be done by a modifying
source code or is that something that
could be done as a part of a deployment
process so certainly something you could
do as part of a deployment process i
would make the argument that in the
source code is actually a better place
to do this though because you can do
things that are a lot smarter for
instance if you're generating the
content and you know that like you know
some particular piece of that particular
page is going to change every five
minutes let's say you can then set that
that cache control header to be you know
cache this for five minutes right so I
think it's a lot harder if you attempt
to do that from you know from your
deployment process itself but you know
in the case that that's not possible
you can do that as well you can actually
do this inside fastly
itself if you really want to just by
looking at you know we provide you know
our customers the ability to use to use
vcl which is you know a programming
language built specifically for this
kind of thing and so what you can do is
just say like alright well I know as I
am deploying things with my CBN I know
that this particular path is catchable
for this long and this particular path
is not catchable at all or whatever you
can actually just set that in the CDN
itself mmm okay you would recommend that
if the developer was able to they would
do it in code because they have more
control and more information so that
they can make better decisions on when
to cache but it is technically possible
to do that entirely from the CDN side
yeah absolutely like it's definitely
like you have much more information at
the origin if you want to set those
things correctly there but you know if
push comes to shove you know it's pretty
easy to do inside fastly as well and how
can a developer test their application
with a CDN before pushing to production
there's actually a wide variety of
different ways to do this you know you
can well if your CDN supports supports
logic at the edge like we do you can do
all sorts of interesting things so for
instance you could actually set some
specific logic that says you know if
this particular header or this
particular URL parameter is present well
then you know use this different logic
instead which would let you then make
sure that okay you know when I set this
on the rest of the site I now know that
it's going to work correctly at the same
time you could actually use the MS for
this as well so if you had a site
example.com to pick up that example.com
you can then send beta down example.com
and have that pointed to a different
service within your CDN or even the same
service with a different like set of
logic for that domain specifically so
yeah I mean like this there's you know
we like to as much as possible use the
basic building building blocks that are
built into the web itself in order to do
things like this there's there's no real
like magic tricks here it's really just
you know doing basic logic on the HTTP
requests and the DNS so in this case the
developer they should push to some kind
of
Kester staging environment and set these
headers to tell their application okay
use these settings for the CDN and then
they can check their page that way yeah
yeah you know there's actually all sorts
of use cases for that kind of logic as
well
for instance if you wanted to be able to
do AV testing at the edge what you could
do is use deploy your new code to one
particular origin server and you have
multiple other origin servers and you
can actually just say okay I will I
would like to send certain requests to
this origin server and I want to send
other requests to this origin server and
I want to cache them separately so if
you can do logic at the edge you can do
that kind of that kind of testing that
kind of you know Quality Assurance or
even a/b testing right there at the edge
as well next I'd like to talk about
cache invalidation I know as a part of
our conversation a lot of it has come
down to the HTTP headers but to make
sure that everyone's on the same page
can you explain the the concept of cache
invalidation and how it relates to CD
ins cache invalidation is just removing
the content that's in the CDN when you
ask for it to be this has actually been
kind of a difficult things for CD ends
for the longest time just because your
when you say hey remove this piece of
content that then has to be replicated
to any server where that content
possibly could have been which in the
case you know of thousands of servers
yeah that could take a while so one of
the one of the novel parts of fastly was
the fast purging system that we built
that doesn't in about 150 milliseconds
and this purging that occurs when
someone's HTTP header says that you know
this content should be expired or should
never expire whatever they put into the
header are there other options for users
who want to tell the CDN when content
should be invalidate yeah yeah yeah
sorry I actually didn't realize that you
were asking specifically about the cache
control header so that that's actually a
different sort of thing I actually think
of the cache invalidation as kind of two
different things there that one is
actually very simple we actually do the
the math like the the time math that's
involved with making sure that something
is still fresh inside the CDN so that
happens like individually inside each
individual node
however having to communicate with
anything else that that should actually
be instantaneous that should actually
like if you're studying those cache
control headers correctly that should be
completely invisible to you the other
option though is actually specifically
telling us to purge something so we have
a couple different ways of doing that
one is to just send an HTTP request with
instead of a git or a head or you know
whatever other method you prefer instead
send it with a purge method and so what
that'll do is that will trigger what's
effectively a peer-to-peer messaging
system inside of the CDN and what that
does is and make sure that that
particular message gets around to every
single node inside the CDN and make sure
that that piece of content that you are
trying to purge is now gone from
everywhere hmm so when you were
originally answering the question about
invalidation you were thinking more in
terms of the API call requests to
purchase is that correct yeah that's
correct
the side of things is talking about the
cache control headers it is actually
quite a bit easier you know that can
happen just independently everywhere you
you mentioned earlier about the VCL
could you explain kind of what that is
and and when you would choose to use
that rather than the headers or an API
called the CDN yeah so VCL seems for
varnish configuration language so fastly
of course is built on varnish that's
what we've been build on all along and
from the very beginning we give our
customers access to VCL and so the whole
idea with VCL is that your your your
programming this request responds state
machine so what you do is you program
individual hooks so one of them is you
know I have received a request so you
you know you say like okay I have this
request now let me look at the headers
you know let me look at the Ryu RL that
was requested is there any headers I
want to chain is there any caching logic
I want to change how do I decide or you
know I would like to make a decision to
send it to this origin server rather
than this other origin server so when
you have that kind of logic at the edge
that gives you the ability to do some
pretty interesting things so one of
those is basic stuff like load balancing
right so I can then say alright I have
multiple different clusters of origin
servers and I'm going to make the
logical
that this particular piece of content I
know is actually on this origin server
which gives you a lot of flexibility to
then be able to move your servers around
change where they're deployed and so on
so when would someone use it and when
would they not you know it really comes
down to you know how much how much
control do you want at the edge if you
have a fairly basic site you might not
need it and you could actually just you
know you plug it in and it just works
but as soon as you want to do anything
that's fairly tricky yet you want to
start doing load balancing based on HTTP
headers or or the URL that was requested
or or to start modifying those HTTP
headers or responses that is we would
use the CL to do so all those sorts of
things do you have an example of a
customer that used to be CL to either do
load balancing or some other type of
function that you would not be able to
do with API calls or headers sure I mean
like actually I would say the majority
of our customers do that I think the New
York Times is probably one of my
favorite examples of this they were able
to use us in order to migrate their data
centers right so they did this just by
using the load balancing inside fastly
right so they changed where their entire
site was hosted without their customers
ever actually knowing hmm so let's say
they spun up a whole new set of servers
or a new origin while the old one was
running and then they configured fastly
using the VCL to point to the new
location of their origin servers is that
correct well yeah kind of I think it's
actually even a little bit more tricky
than that so the thing with a you know a
complex site like that is that it's
never really just one service right it's
actually many right and so this let them
do it gradually you can move one service
at a time and then inside vco you can go
okay like they're requesting something
that's in this service well I know that
the service is now running in the new
data center so let's go over there
rather than having you back to the old
data center so you can move things
piecewise not which is really helps
people especially if they're trying to
go with like a multi cloud type of seven
they tend to put us in front of that as
the load balancer between their clouds
okay interesting
yeah next I'd like to kind of go in a
little bit into how a CDN is built so to
start did fastly build their own data
centers or they hosted an existing
how did that get started great so I love
talking about how the CBN is built this
is where I live and breathe every day so
did we build their own data centers well
no not physically
you know we co-located our servers and
our racks of servers
inside all sorts of different data
centers that already exist so typically
what we'll do is we'll we'll rent space
for an entire cage of servers at this
point but that of course changed over
over the years right when we first when
we first were deployed we weren't even
using racks of servers we were using
individual servers like we would ship
one single server through a new location
right and just plug it directly into the
internet into the the ISPs that we were
paying now of course you know we get
entire cages and racks of servers in
each location typically will deploy
really no less than eight servers in a
location and now in some places will
table up to 256 servers in mystical
location that's quite a quite a change
from when you first started yeah quite
quite a change
so next when you choose a location of
where to put your servers how do you
determine that yeah okay so this is a
really interesting process a lot of what
goes into this is really looking at of
course like our list of customers our
list of users is changing all the time
right and so where we have users coming
from is then also changing and so when
we you know when we decide we're gonna
put in a new data center somewhere we
then have to go let go all right well as
of now where are you know where are we
slower than anywhere else and where can
we find a data center that has the
necessary connectivity and we can get
into you know so what we try to do for
the most part is find places with a high
population density where there is also a
high density of of transit of network
transit right so typically in one of our
data centers we try to avoid the point
data centers that we can't get at least
three different ISPs connectivity there
and so a lot of this is really just for
redundancy like we need to make sure
that like if level three goes down or
whoever else if they go down in that
location that we still have the ability
to serve content rapidly from that place
right so it ends up being a combination
of high network density and high
population density
and when a client is routed to an ED
server you were talking about any caste
before is it just any cuss or is there
also you know custom software or custom
hardware within your infrastructure that
that handles that so this is actually a
really interesting topic that we're
still working on this right like we you
know despite being around for seven and
a half years now this is something that
is a continuous continual improvement
improvement process so the primary thing
is okay you know we we get this DNS
request from some end user and then we
go okay well you know if if this
particular server if this data center
got that DNS request well then this is
probably the closest data center to
where they are to where that user is
right and that's true in most cases
however it's not always true there are
plenty of cases where if you remember
but DNS requests isn't actually coming
directly from the user it's actually
coming from their ISPs recursive DNS
resolver so in there are plenty of cases
where a users recursive DNS resolver is
not actually close to them there we have
all sorts of fun examples of this you
know I believe one of them was an ISP in
the Netherlands was purchased by an
Irish company and after the purchase all
of the DNS requests for all of the users
in the Netherlands started being routed
to Ireland oh wow and so then initially
they would you know we would get that to
one of our UK servers and so we started
routing all of the Netherlands or rather
all of them in the winds on that ISP to
our UK servers right so mmm not ideal
so there's a lot more that now goes into
it so one of the things that we do is we
have beacons on various web sites and
effectively what we're trying to do is
like map out the internet right so if
the DNS resolvers are not going to give
us all the information that we need we
then have to figure out okay you know if
this user is coming from this result are
let's figure out where that user
actually is and try to send them to the
correct data center that's close to them
and so if we collect some information
you know I'm not amazed you know
dramatically anonymized of course from
our beacons and are able to then pick
like which data center is actually
closest to the user regardless of what
the dns says furthermore there's
actually some modifications to DNS that
were made of the last few years
specifically the client eb NS routing
system and so what this does is certain
certain recursive resolvers will instead
of just requesting at once and then
requesting that DNS information once and
then caching it they will request it
multiple times depending on where that
user is coming from so you know large
DNS servers like you know okay let's
take like Google DNS for instance
8.8.8.8 that that can be particularly
tricky for us right because would they
have effectively one data center serving
all of the west coast of the US it's in
Seattle I believe so if we didn't do
anything smarter with that we would
actually just be sending all of the west
coast that is using Google DNS up to our
Seattle data center so instead what
Google does is depending on the subnets
of the users request that is coming in
to them they will pass that through to
us and this is you know again anonymized
information but lets us separate out and
go okay well you know this is this user
is actually coming from this other
location so let's send them to their
closest data center hope that makes
sense when you're referring to the
subnet you're talking about the users
public IP s like a part of that subnet
or
I am indeed yeah okay so typically it'll
end up being like the which referred to
as the slash 24 of your IP address if
we're talking about ipv4 meaning that
you know we have you know there are
there are four octet associated with an
IP address and they just chopped off the
last one which is a reasonable level of
an optimization and based off of the
user's subnet you have enough
information to know kind of where they
originally came from or exactly exactly
so this goes back to that beaconing
system where we then go okay well we
know that you know this this block of IP
addresses tend to actually be in some
particular location right and so then
when we get one of these one of these
client a DNS requests they come through
the DNS system we go okay I know where
that particular IP address is
I'm not going to send them to Seattle
and said I'm going to send them to our
San Francisco pop for instance mmm okay
and you're you're keeping track of sort
of as people visit all these different
sites all over the world you sort of
build a picture of like okay if I get a
request from this subnet
then I should route them here because
this place is close to them exactly I
like to think of it as a map of the
Internet awesome yeah earlier you
mentioned that you used varnish as a
part of building the CDN could you
explain what varnish is and how it's
different from say nginx or Apache the
varnish is an open source reverse proxy
server it was initially built by a guy
named Paul Henning Kemp who's part of
the BSD community and his whole thing
was he was trying to build a very
high-performance proxy server that was
programmable and so he built this VCO
programming language into it and that's
that that's like at its core the big
difference between something like
varnish and something like you know
Apache or nginx is the fact that it has
this language built into it and the
interesting thing about it is that it's
not actually a scripting language like
you might expect the VCL that's written
is actually compiled down to C which is
then compiled down to native machine
code which we then load into varnish at
runtime and what that lets us do is we
can execute that very fast we can
execute that very rapidly so there's
really no slowdown as a request is
passing through that logic and that's
that's been very key for us going
forward yeah I think that at the core
that that's what really what makes
varnish different than the other servers
out there hmm so that's that's
interesting cuz earlier you were saying
that users can write VCL and you're
saying it's being compiled down to C so
that means that users are basically able
to write native code to to run on your
your edge machines I mean yes it around
about sort of way there's all sorts of
protections in place to prevent that
from from going awry you know so the CL
as a language is you know we keep it
relatively semantically limited because
that is the layer at which we can impose
safety on it if we actually let people
just you know inject C code into that
well that would that would go awry
fairly rapidly
yeah because it seems like you know this
is a incredibly multi-tenant environment
so you're saying that the the
restrictions that VCL has kind of
prevents users from causing crashes or
getting into other people's data that
that sort of thing yeah exactly
but yeah I mean effectively every every
service on fastly every individual site
is actually its own like binary blob of
code
yeah I guess can you elaborate on that a
little bit because I like not
necessarily in the CDN space but in
application development some people go
towards using containers some people
have gone towards using a sandboxed
runtime like v8 so I'm kind of curious
what your approach looks like sure yeah
okay so what our approach has looked
like is I mean similar to what I was
just describing the the advantage is
that something like VCO gives us is is
really something that comes down to
performance right so if you were to try
to spin up a new container for every
request that is flowing through the
system that's really really not scalable
that would be incredibly expensive which
would end up like translating to be
incredibly expensive for your end users
as well
what vcl lets us do is do that you know
a similar level of logic without
actually having to have the overhead of
something like a container or or v8 as
well but we are actually exploring some
interesting options my team in
particular has been working on some
interesting sandboxing options so I
believe I spoke about this a couple of
times recently but we're actually
exploring the idea of using webassembly
for this and the whole point here is
that webassembly again is it comes back
to like being able to be statically
compiled you can compile it ahead of
time into very fast machine code at
which point you can then you know use
this for every individual request as its
flowing through the system without
imposing a tremendous amount of overhead
which is what you would see typically
from something like v8 or or worse
containers hmm that's a that's a project
that you're you're currently working on
that you hope to ship at some point in
the future
yeah we've been working on it for a
little while now but yeah I've started
speaking about it publicly over the last
few months it's it's very exciting we've
been we've been very much looking
forward to it
what do you think are the biggest
technical challenges in building a CDN I
would say that the biggest technical
challenges are actually around
reliability you know as I was alluding
to earlier like we have all sorts of
redundancy built into each layer and the
reason you know this goes in you know
this goes so much further beyond what
most sites actually have to think about
and the reason for that is that you know
people expect us to always always always
be here you know if if the site goes
down for a minute or two that's you know
that's bad you might you lose some money
but we go down for a minute or two
across the entire world that's that's
existential threat to us right right so
so you know we put a lot of effort into
making sure that we are just
tremendously reliable have redundancy
built in and monitoring built in through
every single layer of the system I would
say that's you know you know having
having entered this this arena seven and
a half years ago without actually
knowing a tremendous amount about it
that was a part that was probably the
most surprising to me is just just how
much work needs to be done to make sure
that you know no failure in any part of
the system can actually end up affecting
the entire network that's it's pretty
tricky right because it's it's almost
like the equivalent of you know you go
down the site goes down just like how if
AWS went down you know probably a
quarter of the internet would go down
that sort of thing
right right and in some ways actually is
is even trickier than that right because
you know let's say we have a single data
center that goes down well you know if
that data center is overloaded and then
that traffic flows on to one other data
center all what happens if that thing
goes down as well it's really easy if
you you know it's not well well thought
through to end up being able to cause
like cascading failures like that so we
have all sorts of safety in place for
that but again it was just I watch right
here than I imagined it would be I can
definitely see how you'd have a lot of
sleepless nights thinking about that
problem oh yes how have CDN has changed
from you know the days of there being
basically Akamai you know to having this
whole landscape of players now
I mean honestly the biggest change has
been that move of logic to the edge and
I mean I don't want to toot our own horn
all that much but it you know that that
didn't really exist seven-and-a-half
years ago there's a few that you know
are starting to approach the problem now
you've mentioned but that's that's been
a pretty big change over that amount of
time right and I think a lot of the
reason for that is just that like you
know as sites are attempting to scale
and they're coming to scale to users all
over the world they're realizing that
they can make things a lot faster they
can make things a lot more reliable by
moving that logic out to the edge by
moving it closer to their end users and
so that's been a pretty important change
of the years if you look back further
you know things things have also changed
quite a bit in the early days you know
the early days of the internet were you
know and when I say the early days I'm
talking about the late 90s here
was quite a bit different right so like
the approach that you know folks took to
building CBN's back then it's quite a
bit different than what we do now a lot
of times what people were more worried
about was you know preventing requests
and connections from hitting backbones
on the internet because in those days
the backbones were actually you know
kind of overloaded right like we have
plenty of like overhead of bandwidth now
on the internet that wasn't true you
know 15 20 years ago and so the approach
back then to building a CDN was to you
know literally build thousands of data
centers and put them in each individual
ISP that's not really the case anymore
it turns out that the Internet has
gotten quite a lot better over those
years and so the way that you build a
CDN it can actually be a lot more
efficient now just by by being able to
you know consolidate where you put this
and again kind of going back to what I
was saying about how we choose where our
data centers go now we get to like focus
on major population centers rather than
having to focus on individual is piece
which is I must say much nicer there is
sort of the consolidation of power in
terms of the fastest way to get to your
users which is made it I guess easier to
create a CDN you know then it would have
been let's say you know the late 90s
yeah yeah I mean I think that a lot of
it really comes down to just an
improvement in the way that like the
infrastructure of the Internet itself
like you know it's not something that
folks think about very often but like
you know we have petabytes and petabytes
of bandwidth going across you know going
across the ocean and going around entire
continents now that wasn't the case I
think you cover this a little bit before
but would you say the main place that
Citians are competing in now is in
bringing more application logic to the
edge is that we're kind of a lot of the
excitement is yeah I would say that that
is that is the big thing that is the the
big hot topic for the next few years in
my opinion anyway I think we're going to
see just an increased amount of you know
what you can do on the edge and you know
we're spending lots and lots of time
thinking about and working on these
things right now even even down to
things like you know image optimization
right something you never would have
thought to do at the edge you know five
ten years ago you know you can now do
that right next to you right next to
your end-users which is pretty wild so I
think a lot of what you're gonna see
over the next few years is people moving
more and more of their logic to the edge
nothing that's ever actually going to
fully replace like the central cloud
like aw the AWS is of the world of
course like there are certain things
that just make more sense to be done
there but there are plenty of things
that we're doing at that origin server
that don't actually need to be done
there and so I'm really looking forward
to it personally I've been looking
forward to it for the last seven years
you know in a lot of cases businesses
they they have to put a lot of work into
handling scale and it sounds like the
hope is is that developers will be able
to push more of that work on to the CDN
or on to the edge you know rather than
having to spend so much development time
just focused on that
that is the exact idea yeah like let us
deal with your scale problems and you
focus on your business itself awesome
so finally what's next for fastly what
can developers look forward to coming in
the future
yeah so I think that what we're going to
be focusing on now and really like
continuously into the future is just
making it more and more possible to do
things that you never can do before at
the edge as I was just saying before
like you know there are so many things
that we do at origin servers that are
actually more efficiently done out
toward your actual end-users so again
like that comes down to things like you
know security monitoring you know our
Web Application Firewall has been like a
big important part of that image
optimization and video modification and
all sorts of things like that there's
just so much that we do with the origin
servers right now that's it's just not
necessary and so we're looking forward
to moving more and more that out to the
edge finally are there any questions I
should have asked or something you would
like to say to our audience no I think
it's actually been very thorough but uh
you know thank you everybody for for you
know being interested in you know how to
build a CDN and what it takes to use a
CDN effectively
thank you yeah I think this was a great
conversation and I think there's a lot
of people who when they think obsidians
they just think of you know loading some
images or loading some static assets on
their site but they don't really kind of
realize the full extent of what they
they can do a CDN so I think this is
going to be great for a lot of people to
hear yeah it's a lot different now than
it was in the older days thank you
finally how can people follow you on the
Internet
you can follow me on twitter @ @ TB
McMullen or you know so you know me at
Tyler at fastly comm Tyler thank you so
much for coming on the show I think this
was this was really great and we covered
a lot of ground here great you're very
welcome - thank you for having me this
is Jeremy Jung for software engineering
radio thank you for listening digital
ocean is the easiest cloud platform to
deploy manage and scale applications of
any size we're moving infrastructure
friction and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials and
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco / SC radio thanks for
listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by Archer police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website @ SC - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of SC radio is
licensed under creative commons license'
two-point-five thanks for listening